Hello and good morning every Oh, sorry.
Didn't admit people yet. [laughter]
>> Good morning everybody. Uh uh thank you
everybody for joining this morning. My
name is Dominic Zerllo and I'm with the
New Mexico Department of Health and we
are here uh to be able to help support
uh [snorts] this particular committee.
Um the chair of this committee is Dan
Jennings and so I'll be turning it over
to him in a moment. We're just giving
people just a minute or so to join on in
uh before we get started. And so just a
couple of reminders is we do ask people
to please remember to keep language
during their comments to be um uh in a
uh non-cuss word uh whenever possible.
And the reason why is because we do want
to be able to post these videos and if
there is in inappropriate language then
we uh are not able to post them or it
takes a lot longer for our um
communications and marketing to go
through to be able to do the appropriate
bleeping. So please um you know please
remember to be careful when speaking. Um
and that includes uh even if for example
there's a proper name that does have a
cuss word in it, please use the
abbreviations for it so we can make sure
that you know we don't have that delay
in posting. Um other than that I just
want to also thank everybody for being
here. We also had found out that there
have been some issues regarding the do
or state servers starting yesterday
afternoon. So if individuals did
register for some of the other meetings
and did not get the response email, you
may want to try registering again after
today um just because we did uh we have
discovered that there have been some
issues there and we want to try to reach
people as much as we possibly can. So
thank you everybody and with that I'll
turn it on over to you Dan and so the
meeting is yours.
>> Appreciate it. Thank you very much
Dominic. Everybody, I appreciate youall
being here again today and uh for those
of you that are kind of regulars at
these meetings, I really appreciate your
time and dedication uh to this. So,
thank you for being here. Uh just wanted
to kind of just give you kind of a
rundown of what our meeting will look
like today. We'll kind of start off here
with introductions. So, just wanted to
let everybody give y'all a chance to get
in the queue. If you'd like to introduce
yourselves, then make sure that you put
your hand up. You can always use the
team's uh feature to put your hand up
and that way you can get into the queue.
Whenever you are called on by the team,
you will be able to unmute your
microphone and be able to speak. So,
we'll go ahead and kind of do some short
introductions with the DO staff here
first while you guys raise your hand to
get in the queue to introduce
yourselves.
>> Okay. And uh so I'll go on through
again. My name is Dominic Zerlo and I'm
the center director for medical cannabis
and psilocybin.
Jorge.
>> Good morning everyone. My name is Jorge
Gonzalez. I am the program manager for
the medical psilocybin program.
>> Brenda.
>> Good morning everyone. Brenda Martinez.
I'm the deputy director here at the
center.
>> Uh Johnny.
>> Uh good morning everyone. Um, I'm Johnny
Mushe. I am a management analyst here
with the department.
>> Carmen.
>> Good morning everybody. I'm Carmen
Batista. I'm a health educator with the
program
>> and uh, Dr. Tuckner.
>> Good morning everybody. I'm Robert
And Dr. Truckner, just to let you know,
your mic seems I think you may have uh
using a different one.
>> You know, I just had the boom in the
wrong place. So, good morning everybody.
This is Robert Director. I'm the medical
director here at Department of Health
for the medical psilocybin and cannabis
program. Pleasure to be here. Thanks.
>> Okay.
Thank you all everybody. I appreciate
the introductions. And for everybody
else that's on the call, remember please
raise your hand to get into the queue so
that you can be called on to do your
introduction and just spend about a
minute just kind of introducing
yourself, your name, your location,
where you're coming in from, your
affiliation. And if this is your first
time of attending this meeting or if
you're returning to the meeting. So just
a reminder on how to do that, just click
that raise hand button there on the
teams and then whenever uh you're called
on to unmute, then simply just do the
unmute for the microphone button there.
There's also the star six to mute and
unmute and these instructions will be
posted throughout the time. So,
appreciate y'all introducing yourselves.
Charles, you're your mic has been
unmuted. Just unmute yourself and uh you
are able to speak.
>> Good morning. My name is Charles Cordova
from the New Mexico Workers Compensation
Administration. Um, I'm returning to
this meeting. We've been attending the
other advisory council meetings. The
reason that we've been attending these
meetings is that we believe there's a
chance that medical psilocybin may be
covered in workers compensation based on
past findings with medical cannabis. If
that happens, we're considering the
possible of setting a maximum allowable
rate for reimbursement within workers
compensation. And we're attending these
meetings to find out what data will be
available that would allow uh allow us
to look into setting rates for medical
psilocybin within the workers
compensation industry.
Thank you,
Nathan. Your mic has been enabled. Speak
when you're ready. Unmute yourself.
Nathan Rose Crants, your mic has been
enabled. Unmute yourself when you're
ready to speak.
And just a reminder in case you are
having any difficulties with your tech,
you can always drop a introduction into
the chat box as well and we'll read
those into the record too. So,
okay Nathan, we can come back if uh
sometimes what helps is that uh people
uh log out and log back in and sometimes
that helps.
Ellen, your mic has been enabled. unmute
yourself when you're ready to speak.
>> Hi everyone, thank you. Um, this is my
first time attending this meeting, but
I've attended a couple of the others. My
name is Ellen Shim. I'm a psychiatric
mental health nurse practitioner in
Albuquerque, New Mexico, and I'm a
clinical professor at Emory University.
I have a background in psychiatric
nursing, clinical education, and applied
research with a focus on
trauma-informed, evidence-based, and
ethically grounded care. I'm also an
Army veteran. I served 23 years active
duty in the um in the army as I
mentioned and I have extensive
experience integrating research findings
into clinical practice, curriculum
development and program evaluation. I've
contributed um for almost 30 years now,
excuse [clears throat] me, in research
and quality improvements um on mental
health outcomes specifically, but also
workforce development and patient
safety. Happy to be here um and happy to
be a part of the committee. Thanks.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Eric, your mic has been enabled. Unmute
yourself when you're ready to speak.
>> All right. Uh, my name is Eric Barlo.
I'm originally from Idaho. Um, I am I
joined the propagation meeting or
committee the other day, but this is the
first time for this one and I don't have
any affiliations.
>> Thank you.
Evans, your mic has been enabled. Unmute
yourself when you're ready to speak.
Uh
>> my name is Dr. Evans Ado and I'm a
senior economist with the New Mexico
Workers Compensation Administration. Uh
as Charles said, we are attending this
meeting to look into the possibility of
setting maximum allowable rates for the
use of uh medical when it's um
implemented next year. So that is why we
are here and I'm also returning. I've
been attending the other advisory
council u meetings. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Nathan, your mic has been enabled.
Unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak.
>> How? Sorry about that earlier. Looks
like my teams wasn't working quite
right. Um my name is Dr. Nathan Rose
Crayons. I'm a fourth year resident in
psychiatry here at University of New
Mexico. Um got a background in in
science and research as well before med
school. And um I'm interested in this
group in particular because I think um
whether we like it or not um
the mushroom is going to be um changed
um uh to be optimized in certain ways.
And if we're not careful, it's going to
end up looking like the way um the
cannabis plant has been changed
optimized just for THC. And so I think
the way that we gather information and
the the sort of information we focus on,
I think um can really help shape, you
know, the future of uh [snorts]
um [clears throat] how how we end up
relating to the mushroom.
>> Thank you,
>> Gregory. Your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're ready
to speak.
>> Good morning everybody.
>> Good morning.
>> Um [clears throat]
my name is Gregory Evans. I am not a
doctor. I really appreciate the um
presence of everybody here today. Uh I
am a resident of New Mexico. I live in
Santa Fe. I am if I would classify
myself as an armchair micologist.
Definitely not a professional but deeply
deeply ingrained in genetic um
micological work. Um, I have a
significant interest in
sequencing DNA and um, trapping wild and
new species
um, and known species from wild genetics
um, as well as
breeding known common species like
cubensus
and others. I have a a particular
interest in
continuing the conversation,
understanding where we stand in our
current legislation, but pro building
the framework for research that
introduces
the possibility to identify
all of the biomass that we're using um
in a cheotype
framework so that we can better
understand what type of what dosage that
we're providing people. So the research
for that is
massive and undone. So I'm here to stand
on that soap box.
>> Thank you.
>> Aaliyah, your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're ready
to speak.
>> Hello. Um my name is Aaliyah Dodie. I'm
a doctor of oriental medicine in Santa
Fe, New Mexico. And I've been to
uh several of the other meetings, a few
of the committees and [clears throat]
some of the board meeting, all the board
meetings so far. Um
I one of my um
areas of uh special training is in
nervous system and trauma healing. and
um training and work. Um and I'm very
interested in potentially applying this
with uh psilocybin therapy and um
would love to connect with any
individuals or groups that are um
actively in New Mexico that are actively
doing research.
And um
I guess that's it. Thanks. Thanks for
doing that.
Thank you, Dan. We have some comments
and introductions in the chat, which I
will get to. Uh Aliyah
Aliyah just said, "Uh, that's great
about workers comp." Excuse
[clears throat] me. Matthew Armstrong.
Hello, my name is Matthew Armstrong. Uh,
Jimway descended in East New Mexico. Uh,
interested in current research, no
affiliations, first meeting. Deb Thorne.
Good morning, everyone. My name is Deb
Thorne, doctor of medical science and
licensed medical provider in Las Cusus.
I'm certified and experienced in
psilocybin and ketamine therapy. I'm in
a listening mode only today. I may add
to the discussion as I'm able to in
between patients. T says, uh, "My name
is Taye Davis. This is my first meeting
and I'm a New Mexico resident advocate.
I'm also interested in current research
and how it may be applied to this
program." Uh, Deb Thornne, and please
forgive me if I mispronounced this. Uh,
Matthew Buzzu
Anin, sorry. Good to have an indigenous
voice here.
And Dominic added uh some uh websites
here for us, uh, how to reach us as send
email, any comments, uh, how to, uh,
look look into what the board uh, the
board meetings, minutes, so on so forth.
There we go. Uh, we have some more hands
up.
Let's see.
Eric, your hand is still up. I'm not
sure if you wanted to add more.
Oh, okay.
See,
James, your mic has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak.
>> Morning everyone. Um, and Dan, thank you
again for chairing this. Uh, my name is
James Brown. Um, I have a doctorate in
pharmacy from the College of uh, New
Mexico. Um, I've been pat trained in
Oregon. Um, today I represent a
nonprofit called Five Degrees North
Healing Foundation that is focused on
veterans and first responders. Um,
especially tier one, tier 2, tier three
special ops. will be reaching out to
that community and trying to help treat
those people. Um, and then as well as uh
Emerald Valley uh institute which is a
training program for psilocybin based in
Oregon
and I'm going to be bringing them to New
Mexico to offer those educational
services to the facilitators and and
also to the New Mexico Department of
Health. Um, and I'm here today to uh let
you guys know that we're very excited
about this. And my background in
research um in the past has been with
pharmacy and writing therapy plans
across the board for hospitals uh for
health systems um
and I'm very excited to be part of this
committee. Thank you again.
>> Thank you,
>> Katherine. Your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're ready
to speak.
>> Good morning everyone. My name is
Katherine Waro. I just want to start
with um lots of gratitude and
appreciation for all the people that are
here today. Um especially those that are
uh donating their time and efforts to
this amazing
project. Um I am a licensed counselor in
Los Cusus, New Mexico. I am trauma
informed and I do have a private
practice where I have been utilizing
psilocybin assisted therapy to help
people with depression with anxiety with
um end of life concerns. Um and it's
been an absolutely amazing medicine. So
I'm very excited about all of this. I am
here mostly to listen and learn. Um
wasn't able to attend the last research
meeting. I have been attending as many
of these meetings as I can. It's very
difficult when we um all have busy
schedules. So, I've also been trying to
watch the recordings. I just want to
stay a breast of everything that's
happening and be involved as much as
possible. Not sure how much I can
contribute to research. Um but I
definitely um am here to offer whatever
I can. So, thank you very much
everybody.
>> Thank you, Dan. Those are all the hands
that are up, but we have one more
introduction in chat. So, uh, Kaya
McKenzie, 26-year-old from Oregon,
Minnesota, Wisconsin, licensed
naturopathic doctor and certified
professional midwife, POS wilderness
ranger for 40 years, where I was
introduced to plant medicines of the
southern Rockies. Uh, we have one more.
Uh, good morning. My name is Shane
McDaniel. I'm a New Mexico resident. I'm
a certified integration coach with
cultivation experience, but I am not a
professional micologist by any means. I
am extremely thankful for the space. I
have been to most of the meetings. Stay
warm this weekend. Thank you. Uh we have
Alaliyah has one more comment. This is
my first meeting with this committee.
And that is it. Dan, over to you.
>> Appreciate it. Thank you all very much
and for for everybody being here because
again uh just as uh Cather said it's
like there's a lot of people that are
giving up their time today to come to
these meetings and I really appreciate
that as well because kind of kind of
centering back on our norms that we
talked about from our first meeting. Uh
we really feel that in this
collaborative space that everybody has
wisdom uh and that everybody's wisdom
can be brought together for the wisest
results. So because y'all are here to do
this, this is how we can do a fantastic
job. I'm honored to be sharing this with
y'all. So because of that, each of us
will use our voice and allow others to
use their voice. We will be uh hearing
others and allow everybody to be heard,
avoiding assumptions and ask questions
if there's anything for clarification
and reach minimally and act maximally.
So we're going to try to take things in
chunks so that we can focus on those
chunks. I know that this is going to be
a wide open range of things to work on,
but in order to kind of stay focused. We
do want to kind of come to some
consensus building for each one of these
things that we'll work on. So, as we
continue to work through the research
and continuous improvement committee
will be kind of that ability to flow
information back and forth through those
different committees as well. Um, so
just a couple of things to look at as
well from our previous meeting. If you
weren't able to be here from our
previous meeting, uh we did bring up
some research that already exists. Like
I said, I had done some homework,
brought some things to the table. I
shared it with everybody and encouraged
everybody to send information to the
medical psilocybin email address to
include in with the minutes if there was
anything that uh wanted to be, for
example, challenged or changed or
anything in the research. Didn't receive
anything. So, what we're going to do is
just kind of bring these up. This is not
actually a a voting recommendation, just
something that we'll always center
ourselves around. Uh if you do have
information for research and things that
would apply to what we're working on
here, please feel free to email uh to
the uh medical psilocybin email address.
Let me see if I can bring that up here
for you all too. So this is the email
address and just as a reminder for this
as well. So instead of just sending like
random information to this email
address, I would encourage and thank you
very much Nam for dropping it in the
chat as well for y'all uh to when you
send it, if this is for the RACI
committee, please put that in the
subject line, but if you're going to
include any information like if you're
going to include links to things that
you would like to include for this
minutes, just make sure that you
summarize exactly what you mean for that
link to include. uh if you are including
a document if that document can be found
on the web there's no reason to include
the document itself as a PDF you can
just include the link um and that way
again just as a way instead of saying
like here's a whole bunch of things for
you to look at say that this is
something to look at this particular
area this particular thing highlight the
information that you would like us to
see because then I'll be able to take a
look at it and then bring it back to the
committee to see if it's something to
include into our research body if you
will. So, I don I hope that kind of
summarized some of the things that helps
on the all side.
>> Uh, it does, Dan. And just so everybody
knows, we kind of put that information
uh into the chat as well, including the
emails. Um, and a little bit earlier, I
had done some of the other websites so
that people can see them if you want to
go and see. Um the only thing just as a
reminder is uh while our IT in putting
things up on the website does uh as best
of a job as they can they're dealing
with it with regard to the entire uh
agency and especially with legislative
session it can take a little bit. So we
just ask please give it 5 to 10 business
days although it has usually been
quicker than that. So, uh, we just ask a
little bit of grace with regard to that.
Um, because it's not just this
committee, as many people know, there's
seven committees plus the advisory
board. And so, we are making our IT
staff work very hard in trying to do
this. And so, we appreciate it and we do
want to hear the or get the records. We
just uh, you know, give us a little bit
of time to get it up there. So, thank
you everybody.
>> Thanks.
>> Thank you, Jen.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And this will be good
because we have some time between this
meeting and the next meeting that we'll
have which will be March 6th. Um so just
in case you do have anything to add. Uh
what right now that we're working on of
course is uh some some information that
we're trying to get to the uh main
advisory board which will be on
propagation and then ultimately on
training. We want to get a few of those
kind of recommendations stood up
immediately. Uh and again remember that
some of this stuff will be standing up
uh frameworks that will be the early
phases of the program. So it will have
potential to expand in the future and
that's what this committee can help with
is to bring things through it. But uh at
the moment we're going to focus on
helping those other committees stand
their uh recommendations up as well. So
just as kind of I'll go through this.
This will also be posted uh to our
meetings page after the meeting. So, if
you're like, I can't read all this stuff
right now, you can definitely take a
look at it after it's posted online to
click on the links and such. Just a few
things I did want to highlight. A few
things that are already out there when
it comes to code of ethics and equity
resources, uh, as well as informed
consent and risk screening, uh,
information that might be helpful and
then harm reduction education. So, some
of these research items will be focused
on for the next work between this
meeting and the next meeting. So, I just
wanted to kind of share that
information. Again, if there's any
potential research or or uh other things
that might be included in this, please
share that to the email address so that
we can get those included. We can look
at Remember, we prefer primary uh
research more than secondary. And this
group will also be analyzing some of
those research studies to look for bias
or anything that might be uh something
that we need to keep an eye out for. So,
I really appreciate y'all's eyes and
thoughts on these kinds of things here.
Um, Aaliyah in the comments that said
this committee or anyone has links to
some great research that would be great
to be able to access. How do we find
these links that you posted on? So, uh,
yeah, that's one of the things that we
want to make sure that we've get up
after this meeting is this entire body
of documents. So, thanks Gregory for for
mentioning tried to access some of the
drop box links from the first meeting up
force. So, I'll just kind of let the
staff say that after this meeting in the
next uh 5 to 10 days that this
information will be posted for our
meeting uh links and minutes.
Okay. So, on our next part that we did
want to take a look at is the data
collection system. So, if you were here
for our first meeting, I introduced some
elements that we could potentially look
at for a data collection system for the
New Mexico medical psilocybin program to
help kind of center our ideas around
what we wanted to have collecting,
especially since this is a medical
program and we can utilize this
information to help with research. Um,
some of you in your introductions had
mentioned that as uh something that's
very interesting to look at and to to be
thoughtful of. So, I'm hoping that as we
go through these next couple of slides,
I would love to stop at the end of each
one of the slides and just let everybody
kind of provide whatever comments that
you might like to have to challenge an
element uh or to consider other elements
that we might need to add into that. So,
this is where I'd like to provide a
little bit more interaction as we go
through this so that we can come up with
some consensus kind of after every page,
if you will. Our first page for data
collection uh would be uh centered
around the patient uh the demographics
and social determinants uh for this
patient. So going to the fact that we
know that uh the information needs to be
very well secured and we're not uh uh
looking to collect this information in
an unsecured system. The department of
health has great uh resources in order
to make this happen. So I'll just put
that out the preface at the beginning.
But uh a patient identifier, notice
there's no names or any other things in
here, but a patient identifier is
utilized. Date of birth, sex at birth,
because the pharmarmacics can have an
effect on sex at birth. Again,
challenge. I' love to hear thoughts,
opinions. Is that something that we need
to have in the system? Gender identity,
race, ethnicity, tribal affiliation,
household income, and veteran status all
for equity inclusion purposes,
especially for um the zip code as well.
so that we know that the medical
psilocybin program is accessible through
urban and uh uh rural areas. So for this
first page of data collection elements
of course things might be added and uh
changed later on but for today I would
love to open up any discussion if
anybody has any thoughts on this
information on this page first and you
can definitely use the chat or raise
your hands as you did for your
introductions in order to make your
comments please.
Oh, I think you're on mute as well. Let
me open your microphone up here real
quick.
>> I got it. I got it. [laughter]
Thank you, Dad.
Uh, Ellen, your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're ready
to speak.
I'm sorry, Ellen. Your mic has been
enabled. Please unmute yourself when
you're ready to speak.
>> Oh, there you go. Can you hear me? Yeah.
>> Yes, we can. Thank you.
>> Having microphone things. I was just
curious are so from a burden of the
provider's perspective. I guess I just
was curious if you're so you're looking
at either creating or having a database
that this information would be put in
then that anyone who's seeing anyone and
using psilocybin would be That that's
the intention.
>> The intention that is correct. The
intention is to have a data collection
system uh to to kind of keep track of
sessions to keep track of dosing to keep
track of the uh medicine as it is
created and the COAs come in to so
basically a data tracking system so that
this is uh again utilized for um
challenging event research uh follow-ups
and such. So that's correct.
Um if there's any other com Yes.
>> There's some com there are some comments
in in the chat. Um let's see if this
committee or anyone has links uh or some
great research that would be great to be
able to access and uh how do we find
these links uh you've posted on the
website. I can uh put that in the chat
in just a moment. Uh, Gregory says, "Uh,
I tried to access some of the Dropbox
links from the media and got 404s.
I was just looking into that and uh I'll
see what I can what is going on there.
Uh, there are people working with
psilocybin in the process of dealing
with gender dysphoria and I'd be happy
to reach out for comment on how to
approach the gender assigned at birth if
that would be useful." Uh, Charles
Cordova, it might be worth including a
data element to identify first
responders. Okay, that's all for chats
and hands. Dan,
>> thank you very much. Uh, and uh,
Charles, thank you very much for
recommending uh, first uh, responder
element. Um, I would love to open this
up a little bit for discussion uh,
especially for for you to maybe make
some like deeper recommendation on that.
Uh, and so let me ask in your idea of
what that would look like. Would it be a
uh dare I say like a true false uh uh
kind of a field in which the person is
identified as a first responder or not?
And what would the definition kind of be
around that so we can bring
clarification? Uh if you might raise
your hand if you wanted to share a
little bit more about that, Charles, I
would love to hear it too.
>> Thanks.
Um, the reason I'm mentioning this is
because first responder status has
implications [clears throat] in workers
compensation.
Um, as far as a specific data element
field is, you could have a yes no
indicator or you could have an
occupation field if you were looking for
something more general. uh an occupation
field would enable you to do research to
see if there's differences in specific
occupations
um and how medical psilocybin therapy
affects those occupations and the
specific requirements that those
occupations have for treatment. Um if
you're simply looking for an indicator
to say whether or not it's a first
responder and if that has any legal
implications, you could just do a yes no
indicator.
anything deeper than that though um I'm
not an expert in this field and I'm
mostly watching these to learn more as
opposed to having too much advice to
give on it.
>> Perfect. Thank you very much for
clarifying that. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Charles. There's a couple of
there's some comments in the chat. Uh I
think age is appropriate but not date of
birth.
James says, "I have lots of research
article links. Please email and uh with
this contact info in there if you're
interested. Uh Aaliyah says for people
that are using medical psilocybin if we
want to give info for the research what
about the issue that it's not fully
legal to use the New Mexico yet?
Katherine Waro says if we include first
responders would vets might also have
specific information that might be
available.
>> Thanks appreciate the comment.
>> Yeah, sorry there's one more that I
skipped uh by accident. Uh this is a new
JAMA article out on psilocybin retreats.
I will send link via email. We can
include that in the minutes the link.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> So u y
>> Dan, sorry if I may. I just want to
address one of the earlier comments. I'm
not sure who had made it um just because
there's so been so many comments, but
they had said they had tried accessing
some of the links. If whoever that was
who had said that would send us an email
to the medical.solic psilocybin. I'm
actually trying to go through myself in
those last records and uh there are a
lot of different links and so uh all the
ones I've tried so far I've been able to
access on a non do but if you can go
ahead and send it through email whoever
had said that and then um we will go
ahead and we'll check on those um
specific links to see what may the case
may be and how we can correct them. So,
[snorts] and that's the case. By the
way, if anybody if you're going through
those previous records and you run into
those issues, just email us at the
medical.silocybin
email and we will check into it. Um, as
I mentioned in the very beginning of the
meeting, sometimes there are issues from
a server level that really have nothing
to that we can't really do very much
about and going and looking a little bit
later tends to work uh as well. But um
we want to we would like to be aware of
it so we can also ask our it to
potentially track down a problem
especially if it persists for more than
a brief bit of time. So thank you
everybody. Sorry for that little uh
logistical bit of information.
>> Thank you Dominic.
>> Thank you and I'll address a couple of
these things just so that we can bring
these up. Uh Ellen, thank you very much
for talking about the the do part. Um I
I can understand where that might be a
concern. So my question back to you on
this and then of course then for the
rest of the group to uh to visit on this
is that the specific do may not be
required but how about year of birth?
Would that be more what you would feel
for the research base and for tracking
purposes in this be more appropriate?
Ellen, I would love to hear your
thoughts on that since that was your
comment.
>> Oh yeah, I could just type it in. But
yeah, I think that year of birth would
make the most sense. Thank you.
>> Appreciate you bringing that up. This is
exactly why I wanted to have everybody's
eyes on this because that is exactly so
year of birth instead of do ob. Gotcha.
Thank you. Anybody else wanted to push
back against that kind of a change?
>> Thank you. Not seeing anything. Then uh
the next one that I did see from Malia
was um it's not fully legal to use in
New Mexico yet. And that is correct uh
because we do not have the regulation
stood up but the law that the bill that
was passed is written. So this would be
the entire regulatory framework to get
it to the point of being legal in New
Mexico because psilocybin would be
utilized as a medical program. Um so
that's kind of all the comment that I
have necessarily on that one. Uh
Katherine's comment on uh include first
responders. Would vets also be specific
information be valuable? Yes. And that
was the reason why uh it was brought up
to add this as a data field or veteran
status um yes no branch. Um again the
comment could be like do we need to have
that specific information but uh
especially because that was brought up
uh as to be something very specific. We
thought we would include it and to uh
listen on the idea of having the first
responders element or maybe an
occupation element idea is something
that we can definitely kind of bring
this up. and Matthew's uh comment that
just popped into the chat, would asking
first responders to identify themselves
scare some of them away or this would be
an optional field. It's an optional
field more for equity and inclusion. So
again, um some of these things may be
the same thing on the occupation if
somebody does not want to dulge. I'm
assuming and this this is not a
requirement. It is just something for
data and research purposes that would be
helpful. So I'm I'm assuming that's
exactly what that is.
Ellen uh Dan Ellen has another question
here. Do we want to consider where they
are being referred from?
>> I'll uh if possible, Ellen, would you
mind opening your mic and kind of
explaining a little bit more about that
specifics?
Well, I'm I mean I and this has come up
in some of the other meetings just
really how people can access this
treatment is that especially when you
might be in something like paliative
care or hospice that that aren't um
maybe encouraging you know that that you
do this in any way or obviously part of
that is the education of the community
but um I'm just curious if we can kind
of find what maybe are more successful
or unsuccessful ways that people can be
brought into this care. Thanks.
>> Yeah. And so the referral from would be
in your mind what kind of an element
what kind of data would be in that
referral from element.
>> Sorry I'm not I wasn't able to unmute
again. Um I I was just thinking in the
sense of is it like therapist is
recommending this is primary care are
they selfreerring
is there a way to self-reer you know
when someone just comes in um I'm just
curious as to kind of what that process
is going to be for patients in general.
Thanks.
>> Thank you. Thanks for clarifying that.
Um, I'll be happy to include that as
kind of a a field that we can take a
look at especially for our next meeting
and to think about what that data might
be looking at. Um, and couple of
comments that came in on this. So, thank
you very much for uh, Dominic for
including this. All items would have the
inclusion of prefer not to answer. It's
something we always include from our
center. Also, participation is always
voluntary. So, that clarifies that idea
of the required fields man you know
optional kind of things there. So that
that way data could be collected and
then of course if it was opted out of
then would not be collected. Uh
[clears throat] Katherine it's important
to make this clear the purpose of
collecting the info since co made a
requirement for vets participating in
psilocide to be reported to the VA. Uh
Aaliyah's uh question was so for
research purposes and not to expose
people's names that are using psilocyome
medically can the info be submitted
without their name? Um I was intentional
when I created this data element field.
If you notice, there's no name on it.
So, for that specific reason, it is not
to track the individual person's name.
It's just for the research and reporting
purposes here.
>> There was also Yeah, Dominic responded
to Aaliyah as well as it would be an
anonymous unique ID.
>> Great. Well, thank you. Um, any other
further comments and questions on on
just this part because there's a few
more data elements that I'd like for you
to take a look at and then provide some
feedback on.
Next one, part two of this would be um
getting some clinical baseline
information about this uh particular
record set. Uh first would be primary
diagnosis uh built into the bill are
four very specific ones currently uh
with the ability to expand as the
program grows. that those four there
have ICD10 codes that have been
identified as a recommendation already
from the patient qualifications
committee uh that the board will be
looking at to to approve for those ICD10
codes specifically. Uh couple of other
things that would be in here. Diagnosis
duration because uh just how many months
has this diagnosis been for the patient.
Uh just so is this a chronic or is this
acute? Uh and especially for treatment
resistant conditions going into that you
know treatment history would be
something for example uh treatment
resistant to depression is one of the
patient qualifications at the moment in
the law. uh and so that would be usually
identified as two or more uh
anti-depressants that did not uh
necessarily help with the depression. So
therefore that way we can collect that
the treatment resistant status and then
um a baseline severity. So based upon
things like the PTSD or the end of life
anxiety or or anything else that is part
of those patient uh qualifications just
having a baseline severity score on some
of the and if you're like what are some
of these things those are included in
the research part just previously some
of these uh self-reportable and uh
facilitator uh le kind of scale scores
that can be put in especially to see is
the psilocybin treatment helping. So
those kind of scaled scores could be uh
uh offered again through the treatment
sessions and to see if it has improved
their scores uh for that uh baseline.
So I'll uh let anybody kind of comment
back on this set of elements uh while I
read into just raise your hand if you'd
like to and I'll read into the from the
chat here. Lealyah, where do we access
the data field to fill out for people?
Right now there's no place to access
this because again we're just building
the concept of it. But in the future
when the entire program is stood up that
will be something that does get rolled
out for the the providers and such that
are into this program. Uh and if Dominic
wanted to provide any more further
specifics on that one besides that I
welcome.
>> Yeah. So just as far as that goes is
there'll be a system that will be
setting up but yes that is not yet
determined and a lot of it depends on
really what happens within this
committee you know what is going to be
required what is going to be needed you
know there's some additional questions
um for example uh I think the very next
one is about uh you know whether there's
a field for firsttime or returning user
um I think the answer on that would be
yes we'd want to know you know uh those
sort of things and so we once we
actually determine that yes, this is the
type of data type of data we need to
gather. We'll also be doing a situation
where it'll be set up online so it'll be
easy for individuals to access um and
that uh even if the the patient um you
know may not have computer, smartphone,
that sort of thing, the provider will
and can assist with regard to that sort
of thing. So we want to make sure that's
there and as we get all of the details
that's where like the individual
questions will be there. What Dan's
really presenting right now is here are
some of the ideas on what some of these
are. We have several months to go before
this gets established. So as we start
moving it forward, we will ideas are
great and uh the one thing to also
remember is right now we're sort of in a
stage of what is everything that we want
to track. But one of the things that we
hear very clearly from not just uh
programs in Oregon for example where
data collection actually impeded service
in many situations and they're revising
that but also in other programs in the
past where sometimes it sounds great
that we want to gather all that
information because it's a an audience
that we can gather everything about. But
we have to be very intentional about
what that data is because if it just
sits in a file somewhere and is never
getting used, there is no point in
taking the time to collect it. And so
part of what we're looking at is here's
the brainstorm phase. So we're getting
everything possible and then it'll all
get whittleled down a little bit to what
are exactly the parts that are needed.
And the other part to remember is we'll
be doing periodically we will also be
doing things like point in time surveys
or studies you know questionnaires
asking people and looking at that um so
that we make sure that you know maybe
some of the questions that we think we
should be asking everybody. We really
don't necessarily need to ask everybody.
Doing a good sampling through research
methods is often better than trying to
just ask every single person because it
helps us with gathering good data. It
helps us with gathering intentional data
and it helps us with reducing the cost
of that data gathering not just from for
example a department standpoint but also
from the standpoint of time for
patients, time for providers. Um, you
know, some of the stories we've heard in
the past about many different programs
is, yeah, I got to meet with the patient
for 20 minutes and then I spent two
hours doing paperwork. We don't want to
have a situation like that. And so,
please realize right now is that's the
brainstorm time. We're hearing
everything. It will get reduced down,
but in that meantime, say what you think
might be a good idea because if nobody
else says it, it might get left off when
we get to the end. So bring the ideas
out. Um, so sorry if I if it sounds like
I'm on a little bit of a soap box. I'm
also a researcher. For those who al
don't know, I'm actually uh my
background is uh in both anthropology
and educational psychology. And so
researching people, especially when it
comes to substance use, treatments,
infectious disease, all of that. That's
exactly what the types of things I like
doing. But we want to make sure that
this is getting, you know, that we have
a rounded approach and really looking at
it from the communities that are
involved. And so again, if it sounds
like I'm up on a little bit of a soap
box, I am. And uh but I do apologize,
but and I'm going to be quiet for really
a lot of this because I don't want to
influence what people are trying to
bring forward because again, that's the
best way to hear things we wouldn't have
thought about. So anyway, sorry Dan, I
know quick question and there I went off
for five minutes.
>> No, that's exactly what because you've
addressed a lot of those kind of
concerns that are here because that's
exactly it. This is not we're not today
building the system that is going to be
rolled out on the first day. The idea
here is for us to then analyze this to
see if this is something should we
include, should we not include, should
it be optional, is this something that
would be helpful for certain
practitioners to have. Uh so again, and
that's why for those of you that are on
here that are facilitators,
practitioners, clinicians, those kind of
things, I appreciate you being here
because you have eyes on this to say
this is going to be impossible for me to
do or no, that is not going to add to my
burden. So that's exactly why we need
you here to provide that feedback. You
know, us in the research field, we love
to collect everything. There is nothing
that we like and having so much data in
in our but the idea is when it becomes
the human element what is the things
that are invasive what are the things
that are burdensome and so thank you for
everybody providing those comments back
that's where we need to have that and so
we can comment on this back uh and so
I'll kind of let kind of read back into
the record some of the comments that
have been coming in the chat.
>> Sure. Sure. I I will get to the comments
in just a second. I will uh allow the
mic for James. Uh your mic isn't
enabled. Please unmute yourself when
you're ready to speak.
>> Thank you again everyone. Um Dan, my
thought on this is great so far. I know
we got more coming here. Um, but with
the primary diagnosis and the wording, I
just want to make sure with some of the
wording that, you know, with cancer,
right, it's early, latent, some of the
wording might need to just I want to
make sure we inclusion everybody so that
if when they do get to the sections
um that that was my thought on this
stuff, too, was like I know it says
chronic, you know, and stuff like that,
but you know, when you're talking about
cancers and stuff, sometimes it's early
or latent
um or you know, those type of thoughts.
That's I was thinking and then the other
thought I was thinking Dan was um who's
going to be administering this or or
telling the patient to go fill this out?
Is that the responsibility of where's
that responsibility lie? And so that was
my other question is is is that going to
be the responsibility of the facilitator
or will that be the responsibility of
the specific um center or both you know
so just thoughts.
>> Thank you. And I won't be able to
specifically answer that since I don't
you know have the recommendation of you
know who will be filling this out. So
this is just from my thought standpoint
again. So the slings and arrows can come
to my brain then. Um but as a uh as a
qualifying patient comes into a center
or a facilitator that this information
would be gathered on some sort of
intake. Again, I'm ass I'm I'm assuming
again, I'm not a facilitator
practitioner, so I can't speak
specifically, but I'm assuming if
anybody is doing that, there is some
form of intake uh and qualification that
is taken place by the facilitator/center
for a patient. And so these would be
part of those data elements to collect
again either on a mandatory slash or
optional basis.
Hey Dan. Uh, I'll read some of the
comments and there are also some hands
up. So I will do with the chat first.
Um, [clears throat]
uh, so there was a comment by Shane.
Where'd you get this information that
Colorado requires vets to be reported? I
don't think this is correct, but I could
be wrong. Uh, and then there were some
concerns from Ellen about uh, not to add
more, but also something related to
intention of the patient uh, in this set
of data. We also kind of heard how
burdensome this will be to all
intention, expectations, hopes and
fears. And it sounds like uh Dominic
addressed that. Uh and this is literally
your soap box meestro and thank you for
holding this. That was uh from Gregory
to uh Dominic. I'm assuming
uh he is our maestro. That is uh from
Nathan uh rather than uh first time or
returning user number of prior
treatments might be more useful.
And then from Deb prescriber, I would
assume who has a uh DEA license. And
then also from Shane also, what other
medicines have been used in the past and
what were the results? And then Nathan
added or at least a mental health
provider who is trained to provide these
evaluations such as PHQ9, etc. Uh and
now we'll go back to uh the hands that
were raised. We have uh Gregory, your
mic has been enabled. Please unmute
yourself when you're ready to speak.
>> Um I think just like layering in some
perspective here.
The
[snorts] and I actually do want to hear
Katherine Warner speak on this because
she's been actively doing intakes and
recording data over [clears throat]
several years. Um, and I know Deb is
busy and probably won't be able to talk,
but if there's anybody else that's like
has actively been doing this, like I
think there are layers to it. It's like
and and the context of what we decide in
further like committees and meetings
throughout the year like who is licensed
to do what. I saw a comment about DEA. I
don't think my understanding that we're
trying to, you know, manage that
ourselves. So we won't let's say in an
ideal world we like you know like
[clears throat] we still need to decide
if it's a family doctor a medical doctor
a psychiatrist
a psychologist or a therapist or
somebody who's otherwise licensed like
whatever those requirements are will be
fit. somebody says, "Hey, I think you
should engage with this. You may need to
talk to this person to get this
recommendation blahy blah." But I think
that there's like an initial intake when
it's like we start the process. And if
the system that we develop is one that
is not, hey, it's Tuesday, come in
Friday. We're going to blast you off to
the next dimension and then uh let you
go about your life. I think like our
intention is more one of care and
continued support. So like that support
being multiple months before of
preparation before before a journey as a
mechanism of harm reduction and you know
just like this is mental health like
it's not just this one little journey.
It's like this big old shift of life.
And so it's like those intake forms
could be more thoughtful like for the
context of the space, right? So like if
I'm going to see a psychiatrist and
they're asking me like like they just
give me the DSM form and I fill it out
and I'm like, "Yeah, I'm depressed today
or whatever, you know, it's like that
all just goes in the catalog and nobody
looks at it." But [clears throat] if we
could incorporate some type of system
where vocal recognition like is
recorded, is interpreted, emotion,
honesty, actual depth of experience.
When we're talking about treatment
history, who are we talking to? Are we
talking to the prescribing clinician or
are we talking to the actual facilitator
who is like been through the the the
kind of like the merc? See, I corrected
myself. I caught it before it happened.
I'm working on it everyone. Brian,
>> no beeping.
>> It's just been been through the merc
with with you like your your response
and honesty with that person is going to
be very very different. And
from my perspective, what I want to
research is like
like from the chemical perspective, what
are our inputs? But what I can't
collect, the data I can't collect is
what is that psychological profile and
what is that like
um emotional capacity that affects any
type of journey or even like
subperceptual journey like your
>> intention.
>> I'll have to kind of wrap you up here
for
>> but does that make sense?
>> Yeah, it does. Uh and that's why some of
this stuff you're exactly right. We have
to say where does this come from? Does
it come from the referral source, the
primary physician, psychologist, and
such? So, but thanks for bringing that
point up there. Uh I think next one's
with James put his hands up.
>> I believe uh James just forgot to lower
his hand, but let me let's just check.
Uh James, did you have an additional
comment? Nope. Okay. Uh but we do have
one more hand up.
Katherine, your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself.
Uh yeah, so unfortunately I stepped away
for a second and I came back to um
Gregory uh wanting my input. So I
apologize for that, but I am looking at
the slide. And I will say that I think
that would be really helpful is we have
a standardized forms um with there's
always problems with standardized forms.
So I want to make sure I'm understanding
that that there needs to be flexibility.
But if we can come up with a way to
capture some of this information, um I
think it's really really important.
Assessment is critical. Um it sounds
like diagnosis is going to be really
important too in order to qualify
somebody into this program. Um and I
will say that um it is a it is a it is a
process like so what Gregory was
referring to is yes, you don't just like
take somebody on and then dose them two
days later. There's there's prep work
that needs to happen. Um and the prep
work is critical. It's important for the
mind uh for the set and the setting.
It's important to for their readiness.
You know, there there are some people
that this medicine is not going to work
well with. Um especially people um who
have certain, you know, physical
conditions that could be contraindicated
as well as readiness, just mental
readiness for this type of experience.
Um, you know, there are some people
that, you know, if you're opening them
up at this level and they're not ready,
it can actually harm them. So, there is
an entire process that needs that I
believe needs to go, you know, that it
needs to be examined. We need to be
setting that up properly. I don't think
that's for this committee. I think
that's probably for another committee,
right? Yes. But, um, it is important all
those things. And so yes, I do think um
it is going to be very critical to
figure out like who are the people that
are making the diagnosis and also I'm um
you know going to be heavily involved in
the education committee and I want to
make sure that we have plenty of
education around diagnosis so that we're
doing it properly. Um thanks. I hope I
hope that contributed something.
>> Yeah. And we were really just because as
being a facilitated practitioner that is
the data collection burdensome, you
know, that was kind of what I think
Gregory was calling out as a
recommendation for if you could share
thing on too.
>> And we have one more hand up, but I'm
going to go first uh back to the back to
the chat and read those for you. Uh
James on the previous slide, demographic
question about what is your state of
residence?
Uh and then Deb Thorne says you need to
have a good medical screening done
before prescribing. Additionally, have a
good understanding of pharmaceuticals,
drug drug interactions, cardiac and
psychiatric oh sorry psychiatry
knowledge etc. And then James added also
question on are you able to afford basic
necessities for sustainable life. Uh
Deb, I have personally worked with
patients here in Las Cruus who have had
a medically difficult journey here at a
local retreat because they were not
screened well. This should never happen.
Tay Davis, would it be easier to collect
at the prescriber level? This is mostly
information they would collect. And
Gregory added on the last one. Uh but to
that point, we can collect data that
potentially tracks poor decisions and
treatment that may have occurred in a
patient's past.
All right, let's go back to the hands
unless there's something there you
wanted to address, Dan.
>> No, those are I appreciate those
comments and such. So, we'll go to
Nathan.
>> Okay. Uh Nathan, your mic has been
enabled. Please unmute yourself when
you're ready to speak.
>> Hey, yeah, this is just in response to
um who's going to be delivering these
measures like the Madress or the PCL5,
etc. Um it's not Sorry, go ahead.
>> No, I was Please go ahead on that one.
Oh yeah. Yeah. So um uh
um it it in a sense you you it is good
to have some training to to do it. We
have people fill them out at home kind
of before appointments even. But um this
might be something more for the
education committee. But um some basic
familiarity with the folks who are
conducting the ceremonies because
otherwise um a a patient has to then uh
after their ceremony or just before
their ceremony, they have to then go to
their practitioner and have a separate
appointment just to get this you know uh
madress or other kind of measure filled
out. So I think um it would make the
most sense to be able to have the folks
conducting the ceremonies kind of
delivering these these measures or at
least collecting them and inputting
them. And then um regarding the the um
uh diagnosis um uh and who's going to be
delivering the diagnosis, I think yeah
that just it makes sense to have whoever
is um referring or prescribing in the
first place.
>> Thanks for that.
>> Thank you.
Uh we have a hand up.
James, your mic has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself when you're ready.
>> You're ready.
>> Hey Dan and team, just one thought was
we haven't included a question
especially in the front on the
disability. The ACLU would be happy with
that. I think we do need to include
something about a do you have a
disability? And then so we just know
right away there's the those people need
to be covered too. And also that
question should be upfront.
>> Thank you.
>> That's it, Dan.
>> Thank you. I appreciate everybody's
comments on these because this will
help. What I've been doing with this is
taking these ideas and then I
incorporate this. You'll see it here in
the next couple of slides from some of
the data elements of comments that were
brought up from the last meeting. Uh so
as we get to them, you'll kind of see
we'll bring them back up because this is
kind of exactly what we talked about
from our last meeting to add or to
modify or to change that I've got here
in red. So in the session logistics this
would be uh filled out or completed by
the facilitator clinician who is
actually who is handling the actual
administration uh going linking back the
patient identifier um and date of
session uh facilitator license some kind
of tracking on that um for the
concominant medications uh that would be
for anybody that is on any kind of
medications to then kind of track that
uh And there's a there's a wide range in
there for patient safety that that
committee will be taking, you know, a
look at. It's not this committee's
responsibility at this moment in time on
that, but it definitely will be
something that will come up, especially
if we're collecting this data on
research and there are challenging
events that take place after a session
and it can be linked back to some sort
of a medication, then that would be
something to kind of track. Uh the
product lot would be tied to the actual
psilocybin medicine. Um the dosage, what
was the dosage? And this is measured not
in uh mass of the actual dose, not in
like 5 g, but in the actual milligrams
of the uh the the salosan measurement,
the MTP definition. I'll have to get
back to in a second here because I
brought that up in another slide. Dosage
form. Uh one of the things that was
brought up in our last meeting was how
was the dose actually prepared and
delivered? Uh the administration mode is
how was this administered? Was this an
individual session? Was this a diab? Was
this a group? And what was the setting
type? Is this done in a clinic, a home
or retreat center? So, this is part one
of two slides for the actual session
logistics. Uh, and I see hands popping
up everywhere. So, I would love to kind
of get your thoughts and ideas on this,
too.
>> All right, Dan, let me just uh read a
few a couple of comments in the chat and
then we'll go back to hands. Uh, Ellen,
what do you mean by poor decisions? You
mean ineffective care or less effective
care previously? Question mark. And then
Charles, uh, also a question. Is it
possible to get a copy of the slides in
the chat? So, uh, and now we have
Nathan, your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're
ready.
>> Great. Um, I I like all these questions
or, you know, all these fields. One
concern I do have with the uh the dosage
um I think it's a great idea to um write
down what the dosage of the active
molecule is, but because we're if if
you're not using um like a synthetic or
an isolated psilocybin,
um there's likely other molecules that
are they're having some psychological
effect or if not um yeah, any kind of
effect at all. So I think it's probably
also important to um track the lot
number and that will be able to tie us
back to whatever strains being used but
then have an actual mass of that because
there might be some other kind of was
the entourage effect etc.
>> Thank you for that comment. Appreciate
you thinking on that.
>> Thank you Nathan.
Uh there are no more hands but there are
some comments in the chat. Uh Kate Hawk
says uh online
ketamine services generally have
patients do these assessments online and
then the information is reviewed and
discussed in an intake session. And
Dominic uh responding to the slides. Uh
all the slides will be posted to the
meeting record within uh see meeting
records website within 5 to 10 days of
the meeting. And I did post that website
earlier in the chat and I can uh put
that in just a few seconds.
All right, we have two hands up.
Gregory, your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're
ready.
We'll be brief. I just wanted to um
support what Nathan was suggesting in
collecting the full chemobar or the
chema type profile from that session. Um
my specific interest in research is
identifying what chemotype can be
applied to specific therapies
effectively. So like the more detailed
analysis we can get in that the better.
Thank you.
Nathan, your hand was still up. Uh did
you want to keep that up yet? Okay. Uh
if you wanted to add in more comments,
your mic is enabled.
Like yeah, I did want to add something
quick. I'm looking at admin mode and
setting type. Um uh given that there's
already some like um
uh different strategies, different um
philosophies in in how the the therapy
is delivered. Um I think it might be
worth having a field
what what um therapy modalities modality
or modalities was used. And I know it's
it's um there's going to be like all
kinds of issues with just somebody
writing like parts work or you know um
anything like that but um as more
therapies become kind of developed in
this space as as we get more
sophisticated
um I think it's probably a good idea to
to track that um so that let's just see
we notice that there's some particular
modality that tends to lead to more
crises or tend to lead to more something
and we can dig into it and say what are
I know people are writing this what does
that actually mean and we can follow up
with
And before you get your mic off, I did
want to like uh is is there a change you
see or did you just want to just call
out that those are some things that are
should be included the admin mode and
setting type for that reason?
>> Yeah, sorry. Maybe a separate field that
says therapy modality open parenthesis s
closed parenthesis used and they can
fill in like you know which modalities
and I would um
>> can you give me I I apologize. I'm very
[clears throat] unfamiliar. What would
be these what would be the elements that
would be inside of this modality field?
>> Yeah. So some so it might be someone
might um uh try to encourage someone to
do parts work or because some people um
there's some strategies where you just
let people have the eye shades on and
you put on the earphone headphones go
and I don't talk to you at all. Others
will be more directive. They'll say you
know lean in or they you know um
whatever. And there's and the more the
more people do this, more engaged with
it, the more there's going to be a
proliferation of different strategies
and different modalities and um some
probably are going to cause harm or be
more risk for somebody who's depressed
versus anxious or something. So being
able to just leave Yeah. briefly. Go
ahead. What's that? I was just going to
say is like for a data field like that I
mean from from my standpoint I just kind
of like for example I have an individual
diet group it would be a drop down for
what you're describing how would that be
like discreetly tracked what would be
those
>> yeah I mean uh what would be um so we
have on uh one option would be a list of
common ele um common modalities with
like a little check box but um I think
just writing in uh might just be the
easiest and that way if some if there's
uh there's going to be a always a lag
between um innovation and what we're
tracking as a um on our forms. So if
it's just a write in field, someone will
be able to write in whatever it is that
they're calling it and we can we can
follow it from there. And I know that's
imperfect. I mean already like in
relatively well- definfined treatment
modalities, we see a lot of um
differences between you know
practitioners how they use it, but at
least it's a it's a start.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. I just wanted
to kind of make sure in my notes that
I'm keeping as detailed as I can on
that.
>> Okay, no more hands, but we did have
some couple of comments. Uh Dominic just
added that link once again for uh the
record website and that will be
available in 5 to 10 days where you can
find the meetings uh sorry the minutes
the video and also documents that Dan
has provided and that's true for all the
committees. Uh also James question on
what are your current health conditions.
Okay. And then uh Gregory added for
session date perhaps a diet tracker for
past 24 to 48 hours. And we have one
hand up.
Shane, your mic has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Um, another thing that
came up whenever I was filling out my
forms when I went to Oregon was uh
as part of as a as an integration coach
and there are times and and with sitters
or prescribers that
some people
would uh have adverse reactions to touch
therapy because they don't like to be
touched. Um, so we need to make sure we
deal with that in the forms so that
we don't run into problems with uh
somebody that is triggered by touch, you
know, like when I went for Ibagane, I
mean, everybody was hugging everybody
else and you know, and it was just full
of um, you know, a lot of sematic
healing and some people might have, like
I said, adverse reactions to that. So, I
don't know if that is something we can
put in.
>> Shane, I love that idea. Would um coming
up in a minute, I'll be having the uh
challenging uh experiences uh data
elements and if you would keep an eye on
that to see if it might help what you
what you're describing there.
>> Okay, we'll do.
>> Thanks. I appreciate that.
>> Uh and to then let's see what our next
one is on this one. Okay. So, some of
these ideas that came up came from uh
the dosing committee as well. So, I've
added them into this like really like
red background here. Uh but in our last
meeting uh we were having a suggestion
to include prep time uh as part of the
session logistics as well for how much
time the facilitator uh spent in
preparing the patient. Uh then these
next items again are something that I
would love for y'all to kind of look at
as well and followed by the next ones.
Time of administration
uh would be the exact time the dose was
ingested. Anchors the timeline, time of
first onset when the patient or the
facilitator notices the first distinct
change in perception, time of peak
intensity and time of resolution uh
ready for discharge. Uh part of the
reason why on dosage was interested on
this is because rapid onset, balanced
onset or or more um delayed onset uh was
one of the things they were interested
in seeing on the research side. Uh and
again, so I'll let y'all kind of chew on
these kind of ideas. And then some of
the other things that I included before
was utilizing is the session you know
that on using an MEQ 30 score which was
the mystical experience and then a
challenging experience uh score also.
So, uh, those are some of the things
that would be included in the session
logistics part, uh, of of this data
collection as well. So, love for y'all's
thought on some of those kind of things.
>> Hey, Dana. Dan, I'm going to read some
comments in the chat. Yes.
>> Uh, Deb Thorn, good point. Uh, I was al
I always include a consent for harm
reduction counseling and protocols in
place. Uh and then Kate Hawk, as we move
toward using all our resources, I would
very much like to see a way to collect
modalities. This might happen during
preparation integration rather than
during the closing session. And then
Gregory adds, sorry, did I miss
administration method? Example, chew
tea, lemon or dot dot dot. So to answer
Gregory's, I think that on the dosage
form, we could include that in some form
or fashion uh on that, but I see what
you're saying on that true tim.
So
we have one hand up, Dan.
>> Thank you,
>> Nathan. Your mic has been enabled.
Those are all really great questions. Um
I think missile experience score and
challenging experience score is um be
very useful to have. But um you know
those are those we're starting to get
into that that whole packet of of
information that have to be filled out
before and after this, you know, um and
and I I don't honestly know where I'm
coming down. I'm just pointing out the
fact that that's we're looking at a lot
of questions now.
>> Absolutely. And that's why I did want to
have these up because a lot of people
have been bringing up, hey, these are
some things that we could track. So, I'm
bringing this to the group to say,
here's these elements. And then it's up
to again this group to come back and
say, I'm going to challenge those kind
of elements. So, that's why I'll still
leave them up here um to challenge to
say no, we have to have this
information. No, we don't have to have
this for every patient, every session,
every client. No, we never have to have
this information.
This is kind of what this group is all
about. So, this is your y'all's voice.
>> How comfortable do we feel with um
making shorter version of these
[clears throat] like a like a five
question mystical experience scale or
something?
>> I I I would be okay with that as long as
it was again research based the MEQ uh
or has evidence behind it. So
[clears throat] anything that would be,
you know, like an MEQ5 would then have
to have, in my opinion, would have to
have some kind of correlation between
the the 30 and the new five. Uh the same
way as some of these other scale scores
like the general anxiety, you know, the
GAT was based upon a larger element uh
of of perception and reality. So anyway,
just I just wanted to throw that out
there.
>> That sounds like a PhD thesis right
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Someone's got work ahead of them.
[laughter]
>> Anyone's looking for one.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Nathan. Uh, we
have some comments in the chat. Um,
let's see from Shane. Has anyone thought
about video recording sessions and the
legality or ethics around it? I know
that Oregon allows the journey to be
recorded, but only to be viewed on site
at the treatment locations.
Deb adds, uh, many studies use banks as
well. and Dominic
>> only one Nathan
and then Deb uh Beck's department and
anxiety score.
Thank you. I was just making a note on
that one too. Yeah, thank you.
Appreciate that. Yeah.
>> Uh depression uh she she made a
correction added depression beex
depression and anxiety score. Yeah. And
then we have uh Nathan with a hand up.
Nathan, your mic has been enabled.
Um that's raising a good question. Do we
need to settle on um just one particular
depression scale? Because if we got half
our patients using, you know, um yeah,
different scales, then that might make
make the science more difficult. I don't
feel qualified to weigh in on whether
one is better than the other. But um
yeah, what do you all think?
Nathan, are you answering your own
question? I'm sorry, the hand went back
up. I I like the question because that
is a thing to kind of bring up is to
like do we have to like say that this is
the the scale that you use or the I
don't know if we can do something like
that, but I do understand the
correlation between different
instruments. Um but
>> yeah, I wasn't um intending to raise my
own hand. I just clicked the button too
many times.
>> Gotcha. I just was like you needed to
add something more to it. So, [snorts]
um,
and then from our last meeting, uh, I
was calling this adverse events and so
we've got really great and I apologize.
I I would love to give credit where it's
due. So, uh, if I don't remember Shane
if it was you or somebody else, but we
decided that it was better to call it
challenging events. Uh, words do matter
on this. So let's kind of uh consider
that as this. So a challenging events
reporting and this would be uh not
necessarily linked to like the the worst
case scenarios but could be any kind of
challenging experience that was reported
during the session or even after the
session. Uh session identifier links
back to the session event category. Is
it physiological, psychological,
behavioral? Uh a narrative, a severity
uh using CTCAC kind of guidelines uh
that are out there already for lots of
different categories and across a range
of of uh um from from a very light
experience to a very tragic experience.
The intervention, what was the
intervention that was provided? uh if
there is again suicidality that might be
something to be looking at. Uh and then
duration of the and I mean to change
that AE to CA uh on there as well for uh
reference back to challenging events. Um
and so this is something that uh could
be utilized for number one for reporting
of course back on sessions. Uh it could
be something that raises red flags that
there are like multitudes of challenging
experiences for a specific whether it be
a facilitator, whether it be for certain
modality, whether it be a certain lot.
All this is researchable information
that could be tracked back. So again
going back to way we've done this these
were a set of fields. Please push back,
challenge, add, consider for deletion,
whatever the might think.
Okay, we have one comment from uh Kate.
It looks like it makes sense to do this
in multiple stages. Uh entry of data uh
entry of personal data by the client,
medical assessment, session data, and
then followup. And we have a couple of
hands up.
Nathan, your mic has been enabled.
um will there be um uh in this something
that um uh the the uh facilitator then
knows to contact a metel professional?
So I see the suicidality for example,
right? Is there like a threshold when
they're doing the this um the Columbia
the CSSRS um if they above a certain
level they know to call a clinician or
you know do we do we have some kind of
mechanism built in there on I'll say on
our side at this moment this will be
just the research data gathering element
however I do feel what you're bringing
up is a very uh specific thing that
makes a lot of sense on the the and I I
apologize I cannot remember every
committee that we have would that be
under the education training or is are
uh bound to help me out here with what
work group that that might be best fit
with which would be kind of helping with
the facilit I I don't know I I that's
kind of where I would I'd love to see I
don't think it's in my space here but I
do feel it needs to be make sure that
it's caught by some space.
>> Yeah, I I think that's going to be a
part with regard to the training and
education for um providers. Um, [snorts]
and you know, uh, and Greg has a comment
there in the chat about administration.
Part of, uh, some of what's going to
have to happen as we, uh, roll out the
program is going to be, you know, really
here's how to utilize the system. So,
I'll give you an example. Right now, we
do the same thing with medical cannabis
where we have the system and we have the
different uh, logistical aspects, how
patients register, how providers
register, those sort of things. And I
think that's going to really be a part
of, you know, that logistical sort of
aspect. Whether that really ends up in
training or not or if that's just a
piece that we as Department of Health
do, I mean, it'll depend exactly which
parts and pieces, but I think it kind of
falls within sort of that realm if that
makes sense.
>> Perfect. Thank you. Yeah.
>> And we have a hand up. Shane, your mic
has been enabled.
>> Yeah. Um, just want to back up and talk
about the adverse reactions versus a
difficult or challenging experience.
People can have adverse reactions. I'm
not saying that that's not the case, but
my experience with talking to people and
trying to educate people on it is
they've heard that somebody had a bad
trip or somebody had a, you know, a
difficult journey, right? But after the
journey was over through integration,
they were they received healing. That is
a different
story than somebody that say has a
psychotic break or maybe have has a
um
I just my mind just went blank but uh uh
has some sort of physical um reaction um
due to like an allergy or something like
that. So I'm just say I don't want to
say that we can't include that there are
adverse potential adverse reactions. We
just need to be careful that we're
not calling
um difficult or challenging journeys as
adverse reactions
if that makes sense.
>> Absolutely. No, that was that was why um
when at the previous meeting it made
absolute sense because when everything
is lumped under something called adverse
experiences uh or events then that does
matter. So challenging events does bring
into the range of everything that could
be something that is challenging as you
said is like for example you could see
that the uh sever uh the intervention
could be there. So could it be verbal
deescalation? Could it be, you know,
some kind of other integration and then
that took care of the uh the event or
was it something that would be
considered a true adverse uh event that
required EMS transport or something like
that? So therefore, this is kind of the
entire the entirety of any kind of event
that took place during or after uh the
session.
>> Just a couple of comments. Uh Nathan
said, "Good point." I'll follow up with
the training and education. And then
FYI, that is that committee is meeting
later today at 100 p.m. And that's led
by Brenda Bo uh Burgard.
>> And then uh Gregory added, "If you need
the link for DOSA administration, cler
practice," he added that in there. Thank
you. We have one hand up.
James, your mics has been enabled.
Uh just a couple comments on this on I
really like the word challenging event.
Um I didn't know though when we do have
this if if because that's such a broad
term and can mean so many different
things. Dan um you know is there a way
to like click on that or expand that a
little bit because I really like the
word you know if we look at the past and
what everybody else is doing. Um just to
think about it you know that could be a
life-threatening adverse health event.
It could also be a more of a serious
health event. So, I would just like to
see if we could maybe have a definition
for people when they they do this when
they click that, you know, because they
I think there's going to be a lot of
questions on what's a challenging event.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, I didn't know if that if that
matters, if we need more definition
based on challenging what that
challenging event definition would
really mean.
And then
>> um the the other thing I had was uh the
medication if there is a medication
involved
>> um you know maybe wash out a lot of
literature talks about wash out period
and maybe have a section subsection on
that where it pops up you know and it
has like a wash out tab and did they do
a length of time on wash out was there a
wash out at all you know because there's
a lot of debate about that out there
right now right so I just thought maybe
just expanding on those categories in
here that's
No, thank you very much for that one on
the wash out. U because I know that we
have those concominant medications back
on the sessions tab and but there is
nothing on the wash out. So I know that
there is a lot of discussion regarding
um if if somebody's on a very specific
medication that there is a wash out
period that can make psilocybin uh
effective. Uh so I think that's
something to track. going back to the
original uh the beginning of the
statement that you had the CTCAC is a a
wide document used uh you know in
college this document goes from
everything from you know indigestion I
mean all the way through unfortunately
death so therefore it is a range of
different things that uh it could be but
I do believe that uh from the standpoint
of what a practitioner would be
reporting and documenting in there for
example like Alberta's regul ation say
here are things that are uh trackable
and here are things that are mandatory
reportable. So they have guidelines
that's kind of saying you need to keep
track of this or you need to report this
back up to us. So yeah, I think that
through the committee process and such
that would be something that we would
need to to flesh out exactly what you're
talking about there.
>> Uh Dan, a couple of comments in the
chat. Uh thank you Greg. He added the uh
training and education link which is for
later today. And then uh Deb added uh it
really depends on the meds. This can
cause more harm. And we have a couple of
hands up. Greg, your mic has been
enabled.
Um, I would imagine that we'll get to
this, but like followup like whatever
cadence and how much follow-up that we
can find to like
provide resolution like some of those
resolutions might not happen first in
time and I think that'll be really
interesting. But to what the previous
speaker was just saying, digging into
that adverse or the challenging events
type of category is going to be
massively interesting because it's like
you can have psychosmatic
symptoms and defining whether those are
psychological or physical is going to be
a major part in this like um I've had a
I've had reports of people having um you
know like uh
well your body gets cold hypothermia
where like someone came and checked
their temperature. They weren't. It was
like fully psychosmatic and it was this
emotional like experience. And being
able for the facilitator to decipher
between those two things is super
important because that person gets sent
to the hospital, their healing potential
could be cut from being able to like
really dig into that thing. So I just I
think that this is massive work that I I
look forward to seeing.
Shane, your mic has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself.
>> Yeah, back to the adverse reaction
versus challenging. Um, an adverse
reaction um and this kind of to answer
James' question. Um an adverse reaction
would be say they we we
identify contraindicative um
prescription medications
um and somehow they don't get a patient
lies or doesn't you know whatever and
doesn't include all of their
prescription drugs that they're on and
somebody gets through and gets treatment
yet they're on you know SSRI or they're
currently in um opiate withdrawal or any
of those things. Um those could be
adverse reactions, right? Where a
difficult journey is more of
and for many many many people during
their journeys um experience relived
trauma
um where it's really not physically
harming them
or or
most likely probably believe not even
mentally harming them.
Um they're just facing
repressed memories or something like
that and they receive the healing. Um
it's not easy to watch them go through
that. They they look I mean it could be
very
you know they could look terrified and
and it could be very terrifying in the
moment. Um but once the medicine is um
done, they they they no longer have the
anxiety or the um depression or any of
the bad effects of th those um traumatic
events in their life because they've
received healing and and were able to
release them. So I I I I
don't know if that helps, but I I just
want to make sure we understand that
a difficult journey many times is part
of the healing process. It's not a it's
not a bad thing.
>> Thank you, Shane. I appreciate that.
>> Uh and the the next elements, I think
this kind of goes to uh what uh Gregory
brought up was followup. So this would
be a a clinical follow-up patient
identifier linking back the date of
integration followup uh and this could
help us measure what the interval was
between the session to the next
follow-up setting type was this in a
clinic all the way through virtual
depression score PTSD some of these
different elements that could be
administered via facilitator or
self-administered uh and just I listed a
few on there as ideas or elements and so
would love ideas that y'all would like
to consider
in the clinical outcome followup for the
in integration phase of a session.
>> There's one comment in a check from Eric
Vaka there is saying you don't get the
experience you want you get the
experience you need.
Dan that's all for the comments and
hands that are up at this moment. Oh
here we go. As soon as I speak there are
three hands up. There we go. [laughter]
All right,
Greg, your hand is I'm sorry. Uh, your
mic has been enabled. Please unmute when
you're ready to speak.
>> Thank you. I was just typing and I was
like, "Ah, no sense." But um the
uh the I this may be something that is
definitely like practitioner specific,
but it could be something that we
incorporate into broad state level
research.
If during the intake process there is a
calculation of intentions, goals,
um
like projections for the overall like
experience looking at it from a holistic
stance, not just the trip. Then in the
followup, we could track those goals and
the progress towards those like I want
to feel better about myself. I want to
have less depression, you know, and and
tracking like success rate on specific
uniquely identified goals from that
patient,
but that could just be practitioner
based, you know.
>> Yeah. I for for tracking in the data
element I I would I mean I would love if
you have any ideas you know kind of
share maybe like even in the chat like
these are the elements that you could
collect in a data element by
>> Charles your mic has been enabled please
unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak
>> um before I get to my questions I I want
to give a little background um most data
collection systems for health
information and regulatory reporting are
structured around data
um reports and data elements. A report's
typically triggered by a specific event
that requires information to be reported
and it consists of a defined set of data
elements. In this meeting, uh it seems
like we're focusing on a single report
and an event trigger, which would be the
completion of an administration uh
session and then the data elements we've
been discussing correspond to those
required for an administration session
report.
Um, on the last two slides, I saw a
couple of session ID fields, one of
which was a patient identifier and then
another of which was a session
identifier.
Are you considering um adding additional
data elements that would act as match
data for these fields? So for instance,
if somebody reports an initial patient
ID on their first report or if you
assign one to them, will you have
additional fields that have to match if
that patient ID is used in the future so
that if the provider makes a mistake and
puts the wrong patient ID that doesn't
link future reports to the old
to the incorrect patient moving forward
in the future? And if so, what type of
match data fields would you be looking
at for that?
Dan, I let me I can answer this one. So,
um, it's a great question on that,
Charles. Um, and we do that, for
example, currently in other systems.
It'll depend in part on how the system
itself gets set up when we get to that
point to determine what those match
points will be. Um, but that's a great
point and one we uh definitely do
consider when we're setting up those new
new systems. So, thank you for, you
know, for including that. But yes, we
will ensure that there are ways that
that can happen and so that um you know
that it is some sort of a method where
even if a mistake does ma is made, we're
able to correct and uh to address that.
I hope that helps.
There is uh Shane has one comment in the
chat. Uh intentions and tracking are
part of the integration pre and post
which is why integration is important.
And then we have one hand up.
James, your mic has been enabled.
>> Hey Dan, just another quick question and
and comment on this one. Um,
[clears throat] and it kind of goes back
to the last side again just because I
have so much thoughts around adverse,
you know, things or and I'm I'm
completely um with the team on
does do you really need to wash out or
not is going to be very it's in the
literature. There's a lot of stuff out
there we need to talk about. um a lot of
discussion around that. Um and then the
big thing though for me is we haven't
include serotonin syndrome. So if we
really look at the most common things
that are happening in the research but
also in person, serot serotonin syndrome
should be a drop down thing as well as
HPPPD. So HPPPD is um something that
needs to be tracked if it does happen
with a a hallucinist perception
disorder. it can happen and we need to
make sure if if these things do happen.
Um, you know, that's not their journey
that these things, you know, this is
actually a medical condition that has to
be addressed, especially being medical
providers out there doing this program.
You know, they need to be thinking about
that and they're used to documenting
that way too. Also,
what if there was anything provided
besides the intervention, right? So, we
called the intervention. What was that
rescue? Did they provide medications?
There's certain medications that can be
provided to help somebody uh block the
receptor and then that in turn, you
know, uh that journey can be stopped. Um
and so if it's a heart attack or if it's
something that's a hypertension issue,
you know, was there intervention
provided that way? The reason I bring
this up is because we [snorts] have this
great database called the poison health,
right? Poison control center, sorry. Um,
and with the poison control center,
they're going to get phone calls,
they're going to field stuff here, and
we need to them to track data. And when
they do track that data, some of this is
going to cross to them, right? And so,
we want to make sure that whatever we
come out with that they can take that
data cuz I've been down there. I've done
some time in the poison control and they
just need some templates that we can
give them and say when you get these
phone calls, you know, put this data in
for us and then shoot it over to the
department of health so that we can
include this somehow in another subset
for our data. So, I just thought we'd
capture that as well because it just
came up those ideas right there. That's
all. Thank you.
>> Before you close that, Mike, HPPD, is
that correct?
>> Uh yeah, HPPPD.
>> Okay. And
>> usually we'll give like a benzo or you
know hopefully you don't have to just
set it out you know where they're just
>> you know kind of like it's been
described.
>> I'm I'm trying to I'm trying to unpeel
the onion because I think there were
three things I was capturing in what you
said. So HPPPD was one thing you
mentioned. Serotonin I could not keep in
my mind everything you said with it.
Serotonin what?
>> Syndrome. Serotonin syndrome.
>> And you mentioned for challenging events
capturing did you say reception? Uh a
rescue rescue.
>> What was the Yeah. What was the
intervention or rescue that was
provided?
>> Okay.
>> We get really, you know, Thanks. No
problem. Sorry. Sometimes I talk too
fast. I get nervous. Sorry.
>> That's okay. That's why I was like I was
writing feverishly and so I was just
wanting to make sure that I honored what
you mentioned on that one in my notes.
So, thank you.
>> Perfect.
>> Thank you, James.
>> Okay, great. Thanks for Deb for dropping
in that that [laughter] link. I'm gonna
do some research on that one. So, thank
you.
>> Uh, and Greg has a comment in the chat.
Just a flag on serotonin
syndrome. I'm fairly certain can go
digging, but the only reports are when
combined with anti-depressants. I'm
happy to pull that up when I find it.
And then one of the last things, this is
brand new, but um, as we're starting to
build out like again the tracking on the
the actual medicine itself, this is
where and
Do please this is don't ask me any
questions regarding any of this stuff.
This is so beyond my wheelhouse of
anything. So I apologize this I'm the
wrong person to answer any of this
stuff. So this would definitely go to
the production propagation the dosing
those other committees. So please I
would love that but these were
recommendations that were being passed
around on those committees and so and
for the research and uh continuous
improvement it made sense to include in
the data elements. So this table will
definitely get built out as things go
for certificate of analysis and such.
But just some of the things that started
to come up uh for the product lot tying
that back because again the practitioner
is going to be utilizing the product
would be uh the measured amount of
psilocybin uh per gram. The measured
amount of salosin per gram that maximum
theoretical silosin which is a
calculated field an available salassin
fraction. Um and then that a AFP then
leads to what that onset profile
category been calculated and uh that
would allow then for the physical dose
to be calculated by the practitioner
decides what lot is best for the onset
profile. The pro the practitioner
chooses the product uses a calculated
approach then to decide on the best dose
suberceptual all the way up to high
there's ranges that would be probably
provided. Uh so the dose weight be dose
is desired divide by MTP record the
weight. So again, please, whatever you
do, do not ask me any questions to
define any of those kind of things, but
I just was going to bring them up as a
way that could be kept track inside of
the system. So
Donna, go for it, Don.
>> Okay, great. Uh, so Dan, what I would
recommend, and I I think it's great that
you prefaced it as far as this really is
sort of falling in under the dosage. I
would say to keep this right now just as
a placeholder because as these things
get actually uh determined within the
dosage and administration uh committee
then we can expand this on out and so I
would say this really keep it as a
placeholder of sort of what's kind of
come out of that committee a little bit
so far but that we really don't spend a
lot of time in this group discussing it
um just because that's going to happen
in that other group and and it would be
better to have those balanced
discussions there and then import it
here when that portion is kind of done.
Otherwise, we're going to end up going
down all kinds of rabbit holes quite
frankly on it. Yeah.
>> Yes. And I've been in all those meetings
and they're fantastic rabbit holes, but
for me, I'm just like, okay, this is
this is way beyond my depth. So,
[laughter]
>> so that's that kind of wraps up kind of
the data elements that we've got. So, I
thank you very much for the the the
comments and the suggestions on
everything. What I do is I go back I
make the modifications to those to add
in so at the next meeting then we can
kind of bring again to the consensus
over what we discussed in this meeting.
So
>> all right Dan we have one hand up and
one comment in the chat. Uh Greg in the
chat for the record let's get real data
on all slides. Just hoping we stay clear
on the specific realities of risk. Uh we
cannot copy slashpaste from ketamine
and uh there's a rabbit emoji and uh
from Charles
your mic has been enabled.
Um I talked before about triggering
events and specific reports and I had
mentioned it seemed like the data
elements we've been discussing are all
related to the administration session. I
wanted to discuss or at least bring up
if there's going to be additional
reports with their own sets of data
elements. Um, two in particular I'm
thinking would be a follow-up report.
So, if a patient goes in for an
administrative session, this report is
filled out and then they do not have
subsequent administration sessions. Is
there going to be some type of report
that the health care provider is
required to file um let's say 3 months 6
months after the initial session?
Because if not, if that patient never
goes back, you won't know if the reason
they didn't go back is because the
treatment was effective or if it had
side effects that were too severe for
them to want to continue sessions. Um
some type of follow-up report so you
could know why people are falling out
and not going for additional
administration sessions could be useful.
And then additionally, I was interested
to see if any type of billing related
reports would be required. For instance,
um a billing report directly to the
patient or um some type of reimbursement
or billing report from the producer to
the healthcare provider.
Uh so again Charles these are great
questions but this is a part of what in
the various committees they're going to
be making some of those determinations
as to what exactly does need to be
collected what reports need to be
created all those sort of things but
they are not yet determined [snorts] so
uh we have to kind of see and as far as
for cost of treatment um yes there's
actually been some as far as what the
costs in Colorado and in Oregon have
been but it's most likely going to be
very different here dependent upon how
our system is set up because their um
their regulations and everything are
very different from ours. So for example
in both the other states they have uh
fairly high fees for cultivation testing
really in various areas whereas we don't
necessarily have those um although again
that's not yet determined. So we don't
have the answers for that yet. Um, but
our hope is to be able to have it at
much lower cost than the other states
are doing right now because as an
example, Department of Health and for
the program standpoint, we're not going
to have licenser or permitting fees, but
that doesn't mean that it absolves, for
example, cultivator needing to get a
permitting fee from New Mexico
Department of Agriculture for the
correct permits and those sort of
things. And we're still working through
what some of those are. So, those are
going to really affect cost. Um and
that's as far as for the medication and
uh the other part with regard to the
administration sessions that part
because of the federal status of
psilocybin being schedule one doesn't
look although again we're working on
that part and trying to go through all
the legal aspects as far as for
reimbursement but it does look like the
um the integration sessions so the
therapy sessions um actually may be able
to be covered and so in those cases is
that would be covered through, you know,
Medicaid, Medicare insurance, etc. Um,
but again, we're working on that portion
and working on the codes and a lot of
that is being done in the dosage and
administration group. So, I'd recommend
attending that to see a little bit more
with regard to it
>> and
uh address Dr. Evans's question about
the cost of treatment and Greg dropped
in the chat the link uh for the equity
access and cultural considerations uh
committee which is February 4th uh 5:15
to 6:30 the chair is Desba and then we
have one hand up
Shane your mic has been enabled yeah um
Dan I won't ask you any questions on you
know dosing but I will say one thing if
we're going to regulate
um you know the amount that we're going
to allow for dosing you know like like I
said in Oregon um it's five grams right
and I do agree with um Greg that it
depends on the
particular and I'm going to use the word
strain because that's what most people
call it although that's I've been told
it's not really a strain
different strains might have different
amounts of silosin or different amounts
of other compounds within silos within
the the mushroom
that we need to measure. But if we
regulate that, then we're saying that
the ancient healing
um through indigenous tribes, they don't
go out and they don't have chemistry
labs to go and look and see how many um
you know, parts per million of psilocin
is in a gram of psilocybin. Um, so if
we're going to regulate that, we're kind
of tying the hands of of the
um ancestral
um groups that have been using this for
centuries. I think it's more important
that we make sure that anybody that is
providing it has training on proper
dosing in their
realm of expertise. But we don't as a
board or a committee, we don't tell
people
how much they can or can't prescribe.
>> We leave it up we leave it up to the
prescribers.
>> This committee won't be handling that,
but uh particular, but thank you very
much for that.
>> Um and so I do would like to kind of uh
um kind of bring this up for our last
few minutes here. So, we won't have
another meeting until March the 6 from 9
to 11. Um, just wanted to put this out
because some of the things that this
committee is still responsible for are
outcomes, challenging events included,
monitoring, reporting recommendations,
emergency preparation and response prep
uh recommendations. Then it would be for
the first responders in the community
and then patient community education
recommendations as well. Um, and so I
would love that if there are people that
are on this call that might have some
expertise in any of these fields or have
ideas that uh for the next meeting that
we'll have, we'll spend much of the time
of the meeting bringing these kind of
three items up uh as much as I possibly
can during that time period. So I'm
going to create, you know, our structure
around these kind of three things. So I
would love for anybody that's on this
call and if you know of anybody that
should be part of this meeting to
discuss this to like let's start to
bring you know these three things to the
forefront so that we can bring some
recommendations down to the board for
those. Um so that's really what I just
wanted to put that call out to
everybody. So as I said in our first
meeting that we had a couple weeks ago I
said this is what as an educator I
called homework. So this is what for our
committee is like the homework that we
do. will come back to the meeting on
March 6th and I would love to hear
y'all's thoughts, opinions, uh, and
provide information on these items and
we'll spend the bulk of the time on
that. And so that is kind of the time
that I wanted to spend with y'all for
the things that I needed to get across.
Um, this is now kind of the public
comment time, if you will, since we have
about another nine minutes left. So, I'm
going to stop speaking. If anybody does
want to speak on any kind of public
comment in general, I won't be
responding really, but I do want to
allow you the three minute time period
per person to to speak on those kinds of
things.
>> And there's one comment from James. Uh
let's see on outcome side. What about
capturing a question on cancer/end of
life treatment?
Then we have one hand up.
Craig, your mic has been enabled.
>> Um, I'm working on writing this into
official public comment that I can send
in, but I just want to put you work. Um,
I know that this container has been
primarily on the
clinical research, the what can we do
with people's experiences
um, and data we can gather there. Um,
but once we get kind of further into the
year, maybe June, July, August, I would
really like to start opening the doors
towards what we can start looking at for
chemical research and um, you know, DNA
research, like how we can study the
actual biomass that we're
utilizing in this practice.
Yes, no, no response needed. Just wanted
to put that on the record.
>> Thank you. Of
course, anybody else would like to raise
your hand or type into the chat box
anything that you would like to bring
public comment here.
And I'll give one more minute to that
before I allow then this meeting could
be potentially at the end. So, I'll just
kind of leave it up to Dominic. Any last
thoughts you might have, too?
>> Yeah, I just want to thank everybody for
being here and participating. This is
really great, you know, and again,
really at this point, we're in that
brainstorm sort of uh time frame. And
so, the ideas are fantastic. Hearing
them is great. Um, [snorts] the one
thing I do want to caution everybody
regarding is as we move forward with
this work, a lot of it does depend on
funding. And so, especially from a
research standpoint, these are all great
ideas and these are things we would love
to implement, especially as things move
forward, but funding is a big part of
that. And so, um, we we will see what
occurs with regard to our funding
status. Um, I do know again, and this
isn't, by the way, not just funding for
the program. I'm talking about just even
in general. So, one of the other things
if anybody sees things for grants or or
that possibly could fit in with this, we
want to start trying to collect also a
repository of where um you know
different researchers might potentially
be able to reach out to receive funding
to do some of this work even if it is
not the program itself because we are
not the the beall endall. And I just
want to make sure that everybody
realizes that. But we want to try to be
able to help get the word out there
because this is such important work and
it it's going to be years down the road
before we have some of the items. So if
you do have any kind of uh as far as
links for potential research or funding
again send it to us through the
medical.silicybin email and we'll be
happy to go ahead and include it in the
meeting records and as I said as we
start moving things forward and have a
repository be able to include it there.
So other than that, I don't have
anything else.
>> One hand up and maybe Gregory has the
last comment.
>> Yeah, Gregory, your mic has been
enabled.
>> Really? I just want to hear more from
you, Dom. Um, specifically, do we have
limitations? I have not noticed anything
that really limits where we can get
funding from. Um, but like are there any
limitations? are the resources that we
can start digging into. And then also as
a committee, if we come up with research
that we want to like that we feel is
needed for this program, can we just
start writing
legislative recommendations like like
part of what we can do is start asking
for money like years and years out. I
would love to see this start now.
>> So thanks Greg Greg. That's actually a
great question and I'm actually glad you
brought it up. We've brought it up in so
many of the other committees. As part of
an executive agency, we have to go with
the executive budget recommendation. So,
this committee and the board cannot
actually do recommendations specifically
regarding funding. Um what I'm talking
about is for example if there's a grant
that comes out from the federal
government or from a private entity um
that uh that would be around this
research then those are the sort of
things that could be pursued or at least
be we could help amplify that those
applications are allowed. Um but we as a
part of the executive cannot actually go
and um and talk to the legislature
directly for example about would you
please fund us for this. Um that's
actually not something that happens.
That happens as the budget is created
and recommendations are are gone through
from the executive agencies. Um however,
there was the fund the research fund
that was created with the bill last
year. It just has not yet been funded.
Um I do know that the primary sponsors
were hoping to be able to fund that down
the road but because of our accelerated
timeline for the program that is not a
part of for this next year is my
understanding but maybe for next year.
Um but again that will be uh dependent
upon what they do. Um yes research
always it's not just a one-year thing.
It really is moving forward in many
years. And so that's also a part of why
we also look for the outside sources for
funding. Um it's not just funding from
internal and the department of health
for example or HCA and many of the other
uh agencies have a very good track
record with applying for grants and for
research included from like NIH and you
know uh different other uh federal
agencies to be able to do it including
for
uh non-standard treatments. [laughter]
So, we would be looking for things like
that. And I'm just saying casting the
net if anybody sees anything on that.
It's better for us to get things five
times than to everybody to say, "Oh,
well, someone else was going to send it,
so I won't bother." Um, you know, we
would rather get that and uh, you know,
so we appreciate it. But thank you for
asking that question. It's really good.
Other than that, and and I hate to say
this, but we actually have another
meeting that several of us have to get
to. So, uh, I don't see any other hands.
Dan, last word to you.
>> The last word to me is we'll see you all
on March the 6, 9 to 11. So, thank you
all very much for being here. We'll see
you again then. Hope you can spend the
time with us. Have a great one.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Thank you all very much.
Appreciate it. Y'all have a good rest.